Paul O. Hayne

University of Colorado, Boulder

Astrophysical & Planetary Sciences Department

391 UCB

Boulder, CO 80309

Paul.Hayne@Colorado.edu

https://www.colorado.edu/aps/paul-hayne

Office: Duane Physics D221

Phone: (303) 735-6399 [O] (720) 390-9276 [M]

Summary

I am an assistant professor of astrophysical and planetary sciences at the University of Colorado, Boulder. My research focuses on the surfaces and atmospheres of icy planets and moons.

I develop computational models and use the latest observational data to better understand these planetary bodies. Teaching, mentoring, and public engagement are also fundamental to my work.

Positions Held

University of Colorado, Boulder

Assistant Professor, January 2018 – present

Astrophysical & Planetary Sciences Department, and

Laboratory for Atmospheric & Space Physics

NASA – Jet Propulsion Laboratory, California Institute of Technology

Research Scientist, 2012 - 2017

California Institute of Technology

Postdoctoral Scholar, 2011 – 2012

Division of Geological & Planetary Sciences (with Oded Aharonson)

Education

University of California, Los Angeles

Ph.D., Geophysics & Space Physics, 2010 (Advisor: David A. Paige)

Stanford University

M.S., Geophysics, 2005 (Advisors: Norman H. Sleep & Jack J. Lissauer)

B.S., Geophysics, 2003

Mission Involvement

NASA Europa Clipper

Co-Investigator (2017–present) and Investigation Scientist (2015–2018)

Europa Thermal Emission Imaging System (E-THEMIS)

NASA Mars Reconnaissance Orbiter

Co-Investigator (2017–present) and Affiliate (2007–2016)

Mars Climate Sounder

NASA Lunar Flashlight

Co-Investigator (2012–present)

NASA Lunar Reconnaissance Orbiter

Co-Investigator (2011-present)

Diviner Lunar Radiometer Experiment

Science Team Affiliate: NASA Dawn at Ceres (2016–present) and NASA/ESA Cassini-Huygens Mission to Saturn (2006–2014)

Visiting Appointments

Lawrence Livermore National Laboratory

Visiting Scientist (2017)

Planetary Defense Program / Weapons and Complex Integration (WCI)

Weizmann Institute of Science, Israel

Visiting Scientist (2015, 2016)

The Helen Kimmel Center for Planetary Science

Leadership & Service

${\bf Keck\ Institute\ for\ Space\ Studies},\ {\bf California\ Institute\ of\ Technology}$

Study Co-Lead

2017–2018: Unlocking the Climate Record Stored within Mars' Polar

Layered Deposits

2013–2014: New Approaches to Lunar Ice Detection and Mapping

American Astronomical Society, Division for Planetary Sciences

Member of the Federal Relations Subcommittee (2017–present)

Local Organizing Committee, Annual Meeting (2016)

Panelist, Annual Meeting (2015)

American Geophysical Union

Session Organizer (Mars Atmosphere), Annual Meeting (2014–2017)

Young Scientists for Planetary Exploration

Co-founder (2012) and Co-leader (2012–present)

World-wide advocacy organization for early-career planetary scientists

Ad Astra Academy

Co-founder and Co-leader, Ad Astra - Brazil (2015–2016)

Science and exploration program for school-aged students in developing countries

NASA Science Mission Directorate

Review Panel Member (2012-present)

National Research Council - Space Studies Board

Raconteur, Planetary Science Decadal Survey (2009–2010)

Earth & Space Sciences Student Organization, UCLA

President (2007–2008)

Stanford Astronomical Society

President (2002-2004)

Referee for major scientific journals:

Journal of Geophysical Research

Geophysical Research Letters

Icarus

 $Astrophysical\ Journal$

Planetary & Space Science

Advances in Space Research

Space Science Reviews

Geology

Science Advances

| Honors & Awards | 2013 2011 2010 2010 2010 2008 2006 | NASA Group Achievement Award, Diviner Lunar Radiometer science team NASA Group Achievement Award, Mars Climate Sounder science team Best Student Paper Award, NASA Lunar Science Forum NASA Group Achievement Award, Diviner Lunar Radiometer operations team NASA Group Achievement Award, Diviner Lunar Radiometer science team Simon Latimer Award for Service, UCLA Graduate Fellowship, Institute of Geophysics and Planetary Physics Chancelland Physics LICLA |
|-----------------|--|--|
| | 2006 | Chancellor's Prize, UCLA |
| | 2003 | Graduate Fellowship, Dept. of Geophysics, Stanford University |
| | 2001 | Summer Research Fellowship, Dept. of Physics, Stanford University |

Teaching Univer

University of Colorado, Boulder

ASTR 3720: Planets and their Atmospheres (Spring, 2018)

Professor for upper-division undergraduate course (84 students)

California Institute of Technology

Ge 151: Planetary Surfaces (2011)

Guest Lecturer for graduate course (~6 students)

University of California, Los Angeles

ESS 10: Exploring Mars (2008)

Teaching Assistant and Guest Lecturer for undergraduate course (60 students)

Stanford University

Geophysics 150: Physics of the Earth (2004, 2005)

Teaching Assistant for graduate course (\sim 6 students)

Physics 50: Observational Astronomy (2002, 2003)

Teaching Assistant for undergraduate course (\sim 20 students)

Mentoring

Laboratory for Atmospheric and Space Physics

Mentor

2018-present: Carlos Eytan Gary Bicas (U. Colorado)

Caltech Summer Undergraduate Research Fellows (SURF)

Mentor

2017: James Haber (Cornell University)

2015: Léa Bonnefoy (Cornell University)

2014: Clifford Watkins (Carleton College)

2011: Michael Lauria (Caltech)

Maximizing Student Potential (MSP)

Mentor

2015–2018: Jose Martínez Camacho (Citrus College \rightarrow Cal-Poly University)

Caltech Postdoctoral Fellows at JPL

Mentor

2017–2018: Dr. Quentin Vinckier (co-mentor with Dr. R. Glenn Sellar)

2016–2018: Dr. Catherine M. Elder

| External Grants | 2018-2021 | Boulders on Bennu: Modeling Thermal Emission from Boulders for Yarkovsky Effect and Thermal Inertia Investigations PI: P. Hayne (Science PI: C. Elder) NASA OSIRIS-REx Participating Scientist Program / \$346,000 |
|-----------------|-----------|---|
| | 2013-2019 | Lunar Flashlight Science Investigation PI: B. Cohen (Co-I: P. Hayne) NASA Advanced Exploration Systems / ~\$400,000 for P. Hayne |
| | 2017–2018 | Unlocking the Climate Record Stored within Mars' Polar Layered Deposits PI: P. Hayne W. M. Keck Institute for Space Studies / \$50,000 |
| | 2016-2018 | Lunar Reconnaissance Orbiter Extended Mission 3 PI: D. Paige (Co-I: P. Hayne) NASA Discovery Program / ~\$600,000 allocation for P. Hayne |
| | 2016-2018 | Mars Reconnaissance Orbiter Extended Mission 4 PI: J. T. Schofield (Co-I: P. Hayne) NASA Mars Program / ~\$300,000 allocation for P. Hayne |
| | 2015-2018 | Inter-seasonal and Inter-annual Surface Dust Fluxes on Mars PI: P. Hayne (Science PI: S. Piqueux) NASA Mars Data Analysis Program / \$330,690 |
| | 2015-2018 | Europa Thermal Emission Imaging System PI: P. Christensen (Co-I: P. Hayne) NASA Europa Clipper Mission / ~\$30,000 allocation for P. Hayne |
| | 2013-2017 | Volatile Regolith Thermal Investigation Consortium for Exploration and Science (VORTICES) PI: A. Rivkin (Co-I: P. Hayne) NASA Solar System Exploration Research Virtual Institute / ~\$120,000 |
| | 2014-2016 | Thermal Infrared Observations of the Moon during Lunar Eclipse PI: P. Lucey (Co-I: P. Hayne) NASA Planetary Astronomy / \$142,810 allocation for P. Hayne |
| | 2013-2014 | Development of Large Format Rad-Hard Focal Plane Arrays and Readouts for Thermal Radiometer for Europa Clipper Mission PI: M. Kenyon (Co-I: P. Hayne) Instrument Concepts for Europa Exploration / \$16,460 allocation for P. Hayne |
| | 2013-2014 | New Approaches to Lunar Ice Detection and Mapping PI: P. Hayne W. M. Keck Institute for Space Studies / \$50,000 |
| | | |

| T 1 | 2010 | A 11 1 TO |
|----------|------|--|
| Invited | 2018 | Applied Physics Laboratory, Johns Hopkins University |
| Lectures | 2017 | Lawrence Livermore National Laboratory |
| | 2017 | University of Colorado, Boulder |
| | 2016 | Lunar & Planetary Institute |
| | 2016 | Weizmann Institute of Science (Israel) |
| | 2015 | International Space Exploration Coordination Group, |
| | 2015 | NASA Exploration Science Forum |
| | 2015 | University of California - Santa Cruz |
| | 2014 | SETI Institute |
| | 2013 | Lunar & Planetary Institute |
| | 2012 | California Institute of Technology |
| | 2012 | NASA – Jet Propulsion Laboratory |
| | | |

Professional Affiliations

American Astronomical Society - Division for Planetary Sciences

American Geophysical Union European Geosciences Union

Asia Oceania Geosciences Society

Geochemical Society

Sigma Xi

Skills & Training

Remote sensing & spacecraft instrumentation

Spectroscopy (ultraviolet through submillimeter)

Thermal imaging and radiometry

Modeling and Numerical Simulation

Heat transfer (thermal modeling)

Radiative transfer for planetary atmospheres and surfaces

Geophysical inversion

Transient and stochastic phenomena

Computer programming languages

Proficient/expert: C/C++, Python, MATLAB, IDL, bash, c-shell

Familiar: Fortran 90/95, awk, javascript, etc.

Mission formulation experience

Team-X, NASA Jet Propulsion Laboratory

Team-A, NASA Jet Propulsion Laboratory

Capture Lead Training, NASA Jet Propulsion Laboratory

Co-I on proposals to NASA's Discovery and $New\ Frontiers$ programs

PI on instrument proposals to NASA mission programs

Additional training

Astrobiology Winter School and Field Course (2011)

NASA Astrobiology Institute and Hawaii Institute for Astronomy

International Astrobiology Summer School (2008)

NASA Astrobiology Institute and Universidad Internacional Menéndez Pelayo, Spain

PADI Open Water Diver scuba certification (50+ dives)

Eagle Scout (1998), BSA Troop 676, Issaquah, WA

Publications: Refereed Journal Articles

Number of peer-reviewed papers: 31 (as of March, 2018) h-index: 14 (Web of Science), 17 (Google Scholar)

Total citations: 594 (Web of Science), 1,009 (Google Scholar)

2018

 Heavens, N. G., Kleinböhl, A., Chaffin, M. S., Halekas, J. S., Kass, D. M., Hayne, P. O., McCleese, D. J., Piqueux, S., Shirley, J. H., & Schofield, J. T. (2018), Hydrogen escape from Mars enhanced by deep convection in dust storms, *Nature Astronomy*, 2, 126–132. doi: 10.1038/s41550-017-0353-4.

2017

- Hayne, P. O., Bandfield, J. L., Siegler, M. A., Vasavada, A. R., Ghent, R. R., et al. (2017), Global regolith thermophysical properties of the Moon from the Diviner Lunar Radiometer Experiment, J. Geophys. Res., 122, 2371–2400. doi: 10.1002/2017JE005387
- Elder, C. M., Hayne, P. O., Bandfield, J. L., Ghent, R. R., Williams, J.-P., Donaldson Hanna, K. L., & Paige, D. A. (2017), Young lunar volcanic Features: Thermophysical properties and formation, *Icarus*, 290, 224–237. doi: 10.1016/j.icarus.2017.03.004
- Mitri, G., Postberg, F., Soderblom, J. M., ..., Hayne, P. O., et al. (2017), Explorer of Enceladus and Titan (E²T): Investigating ocean worlds' evolution and habitability in the solar system, Planetary and Space Science, doi: 10.1016/j.pss.2017.11.001
- Landis, M. E., Byrne, S., Schörghofer, N., Schmidt, B. E., Hayne, P. O., Castillo-Rogez, J.,
 Russell, C. T. (2017), Conditions for sublimating water ice to supply Ceres' exosphere, J. Geophys. Res., 122, 1984–1995. doi: 10.1002/2017JE005335
- 6. Davies, A. G., Gunapala, S., Soibel, A., Ting, D., Rafol, S., Blackwell, M., **Hayne, P. O.**, & Kelly, M. (2017), A novel technology for measuring the eruption temperature of silicate lavas with remote sensing: Application to Io and other planets, *J. Volcanology & Geothermal Res.*, 343, 1–16. doi: 10.1016/j.jvolgeores.2017.04.016
- Fisher, E. A., Lucey, P. G., Lemelin, M., Greenhagen, B. T., Siegler, M. A., Mazarico, E., Aharonson, O., Williams, J-P., Hayne, P. O., Neumann, G. A., Paige, D. A., Smith, D. E., & Zuber, M. T. (2017), Evidence for surface water ice in the lunar polar regions using reflectance measurements from the Lunar Orbiter Laser Altimeter and temperature measurements from the Diviner Lunar Radiometer Experiment, *Icarus*, 292, 74–85. doi: 10.1016/j.icarus.2017.03.023

2016

- 8. Piqueux, S., Kleinböhl, A., **Hayne, P. O.**, Heavens, N. G., Kass, D. M., McCleese, D. J., ... & Shirley, J. H. (2016), Discovery of a widespread low–latitude diurnal CO₂ frost cycle on Mars, *J. Geophys. Res.*, 121, 1174-118. doi: 10.1002/2016JE005034
- 9. Greenhagen, B. T., Neish, C. D., Williams, J. P., Cahill, J. T., Ghent, R. R., **Hayne, P. O.**, ... & Bandfield, J. L. (2016), Origin of the anomalously rocky appearance of Tsiolkovskiy crater, *Icarus*, 273, 237–247. doi: 10.1016/j.icarus.2016.02.041
- 10. Bennett, K. A., Horgan, B. H., Gaddis, L. R., Greenhagen, B. T., Allen, C. C., **Hayne, P. O.**, ... & Paige, D. A. (2016), Complex explosive volcanic activity on the Moon within Oppenheimer crater, *Icarus*, 273, 296–314. doi: 10.1016/j.icarus.2016.02.007
- 11. Bonnefoy, L. E., A. G. Hayes, **P. O. Hayne**, et al. (2015), Compositional and spatial variations in Titan dune and interdune regions from Cassini VIMS and RADAR, *Icarus*, 270, 222–237, doi:10.1016/j.icarus.2015.09.014

- Hayne, P. O., and Oded Aharonson (2015), Thermal stability of ice on Ceres with rough topography, J. Geophys. Res., 120, 1567–1584, doi: 10.1002/2015JE004887
- 13. Heavens, N. G., Cantor, B. A., **Hayne, P. O.**, et al. (2015), Extreme detached dust layers near Martian volcanoes: Evidence for dust transport by mesoscale circulations forced by high topography, *Geophys. Res. Lett.*, 42, 10, 3730–3738. doi: 10.1002/2015GL064004
- Hayne, P. O., A. R. Hendrix, E. Sefton-Nash, P. G. Lucey, K. D. Retherford, J-P. Williams, et al. (2015), Evidence for exposed water ice in the Moon's south polar regions from Lunar Reconnaissance Orbiter ultraviolet albedo and temperature measurements, *Icarus*, 255, 58–69, doi:10.1016/j.icarus.2015.03.032
- 15. Glotch, T. D., Bandfield, J. L., Lucey, P. G., **Hayne, P. O.**, et al. (2015), Formation of lunar swirls by magnetic field standoff of the solar wind, *Nature Communications*, 6. doi: 10.1038/ncomms7189
- Piqueux, S., Kleinböhl, A., Hayne, P. O., Kass, D. M., Schofield, J. T., & McCleese, D. J. (2015), Variability of the Martian seasonal CO2 cap extent over eight Mars Years, *Icarus*, doi:10.1016/j.icarus.2014.10.045
- 17. Bandfield, J. L., **Hayne, P. O.**, Williams, J. P., Greenhagen, B. T., & Paige, D. A. (2015), Lunar surface roughness derived from LRO Diviner Radiometer observations, *Icarus*, 248, 357–372. doi: 10.1016/j.icarus.2014.11.009

2014

- 18. **Hayne, P. O.**, McCord, T. B., & Sotin, C. (2014), Titan's surface composition and atmospheric transmission with solar occultation measurements by Cassini VIMS, *Icarus*, 243, 158–172. doi: 10.1016/j.icarus.2014.08.045
- 19. **Hayne, P. O.**, D. A. Paige, N. G. Heavens (2014), The role of snowfall in forming the seasonal ice caps of Mars: Models and constraints from the Mars Climate Sounder, *Icarus 231*, 122–130. doi: 10.1016/j.icarus.2013.10.020
- 20. Ghent, R. R., **Hayne, P. O.**, Bandfield, J. L., Campbell, B. A., Allen, C. C., Carter, L. M., & Paige, D. A. (2014), Constraints on the recent rate of lunar ejecta breakdown and implications for crater ages, *Geology*, 42(12), 1059–1062. doi: 10.1130/G35926.1
- 21. Bandfield, J. L., E. Song, **P. O. Hayne**, B. D. Brand, R. R. Ghent, A. R. Vasavada, D. A. Paige (2014), Lunar cold spots: Granular flow features and extensive insulating materials surrounding young craters, *Icarus 231*, 221–231. doi: 10.1016/j.icarus.2013.12.017
- 22. Ingersoll, R. V., Pratt, M. J., Davis, P. M., Caracciolo, L., Day, P. P., Hayne, P. O., ... & Hendrix, E. D. (2014), Paleotectonics of a complex Miocene half graben formed above a detachment fault: The Diligencia basin, Orocopia Mountains, southern California, *Lithosphere*, 6(3), 157–176. doi: 10.1130/L334.1

2013

23. Barnes, J. W., B. J. Buratti, E. P. Turtle, J. Bow, P. A. Dalba, J. Perry, R. H. Brown, S. Rodriguez, S. Le Mouelic, K. H. Baines, C. Sotin, R. D. Lorenz, M. J. Malaska, T. B. McCord, R. N. Clark, R. Jaumann, P. O. Hayne, et al. (2013), Precipitation-Induced Surface Brightenings Seen on Titan by Cassini VIMS and ISS, Planetary Science, 2, p. 1. doi: 10.1186/2191-2521-2-1

2012

- 24. **Hayne, P. O.**, D. A. Paige, J. T. Schofield, D. M. Kass, A. Kleinböhl, N. G. Heavens, and D. J. McCleese (2012), Carbon dioxide snow clouds on Mars: South polar winter observations by the Mars Climate Sounder, *J. Geophys. Res.*, 117, E08014, doi: 10.1029/2011JE004040
- Vasavada, A. R., J. L. Bandfield, B. T. Greenhagen, P. O. Hayne, et al. (2012), Lunar Equatorial Surface Temperatures and Regolith Properties from the Diviner Lunar Radiometer Experiment, J. Geophys. Res. 117, E00H18. doi: 10.1029/2011JE003987

2010

- Hayne, P. O., B. T. Greenhagen, M. C. Foote, M. A. Siegler, A. R. Vasavada, and D. A. Paige (2010), Diviner Lunar Radiometer Observations of the LCROSS Impact, *Science*, 330, 477. doi: 10.1126/science.1197135
- Paige, D. A., M. A. Siegler, J. A. Zhang, P. O. Hayne, et al. (2010), Diviner Observations of Cold Traps in the Lunar South Polar Region: Spatial Distribution and Temperature, Science 330, 479. doi: 10.1126/science.1187726
- 28. Greenhagen, B. T., P. G. Lucey, M. B. Wyatt, T. D. Glotch, C. C. Allen, J. A. Arnold, J. L. Bandfield, N. E. Bowles, K. L. Hanna, **P. O. Hayne**, E. Song, I. R. Thomas, and D. A. Paige (2010), Global Silicate Mineralogy of the Moon from the Diviner Lunar Radiometer, *Science* 329, 1507. doi: 10.1126/science.1192196
- 29. McCord, T. B., Hansen, G. B., Combe, J-P., & **P. O. Hayne** (2010), Hydrated minerals on Europa's surface: An improved look from the Galileo NIMS investigation, *Icarus 209*, 639–650. doi: 10.1016/j.icarus.2010.05.026

2009

30. Barnes, J. W., ..., **P. O. Hayne**, et al. (2009), VIMS Spectral Mapping Observations of Titan during the Cassini Prime Mission, *Planet. and Space Sci.*, 57, 1950–1962. doi: 10.1016/j.pss.2009.04.013

2008

31. McCord, T. B., **P. Hayne**, et al. (2008), Titan's surface: Search for spectral diversity and composition using the Cassini VIMS investigation, *Icarus*, 194, 212–242. doi: 10.1016/j.icarus.2007.08.039

Publications: Book Chapters & Reports

- Aharonson, O., A. Hayes, P. O. Hayne, R. Lopes, A. Lucas, J. T. Perron, (2012), Titan's Surface Geology, in: C. G. Mueller-Wodarg, T. Cravens and E. Lellouch (Ed.), *Titan: Surface, Atmosphere and Magnetosphere*, Cambridge University Press, Cambridge, UK.
- 2. **Hayne, P. O.**, A. P. Ingersoll, D. A. Paige, & 32 co-authors (2014), "New approaches to lunar ice detection and mapping," *Keck Institute for Space Studies Report*. [PDF]

Publications: Commentaries

1. Hayne, P. O. (2013), Abandoned frontier, Nature Geosci., 6(3), 155-156. doi: 10.1038/ngeo1753